Guide to the Robert Herrick Papers 1887-1960
University of Chicago Library
Herrick, Robert. Papers
1887-1960
17.25 linear feet (28 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Robert Herrick, novelist, professor. The Robert Herrick Papers contain correspondence; manuscripts of novels, plays, short stories, and literary criticism. The collection also includes essays and lectures on political, educational, and literary subjects. Herrick's correspondents include Robert Morss Lovett, Jane Addams, William Dean Howells, Harriet Monroe, William Rainey Harper, Norman Hapgood, and Bernard Berenson.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
Robert Herrick (1868-1938), novelist and professor of composition and literature, was born into the post-Civil War gentility of Cambridge, Massachusetts and died in the Virgin Islands, a member of Franklin D. Roosevelt's New Deal government. Of old New England stock, he was also educated in New England. He attended the Cambridge High School and in 1885 entered Harvard, where his mother's cousin George Herbert Palmer was Professor of Philosophy. At Harvard he studied under such men as Francis James Child, George Lyman Kittredge, William James, and Barrett Wendell, and while still an undergraduate published his first stories in the Harvard Advocate and Harvard Monthly. He was associated, either in friendship or through participation in the Monthly or the Mermaid Club, with such men as Philip Abbot, George Rice Carpenter, Jefferson Fletcher (who was to be his brother-in-law), Norman and Hutchins Hapgood, Bernard Berenson, George Pierce Baker, George Santayana, William Vaughn Moody, and Robert Morss Lovett.
After graduation from Harvard in 1890, Herrick taught composition and literature at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In 1893, he accepted an appointment at the University of Chicago, where his cousin by marriage, Alice Freeman Palmer, was already established as the University's first Dean of Women. Here he developed a writing program similar to that taught at Harvard by A. S. Hill and Barrett Wendell, and was instrumental in persuading Robert Morss Lovett and William Vaughn Moody to join the English faculty.
In 1894, Herrick married his first cousin, Harriet Peabody Emery. The marriage was dissolved in 1916; and one son, Philip Herrick, survived his parents. In 1899, the Herricks acquired a lot at 5735 Lexington (now University) Avenue and in 1900, engaged Hugh M. Garden to design a home for them. The local press, chafing over Herrick's realistic descriptions of Chicago in The Web of Life (1900), ridiculed the project as intended to educate the taste of those accustomed to Chicago's "vulgarity;" but the house (now Calvert House) has come to be regarded as an important precursor of the "Prairie School" of architecture. In 1913, Herrick purchased a house and land in York Village, Maine; and this he regarded as his permanent home.
From 1909 to 1923, when he resigned his professorship, Herrick spent only part of each year at the University, the other part writing and traveling. In 1935, he was appointed Government Secretary for the Virgin Islands.
During his lifetime, he published three collections of short stories and twenty-one novels, several textbooks, and a study of World War I. He also wrote frequently for periodicals: short stories (several early ones published under the pseudonym of Austin Smith), literary and political essays, book reviews and editorials. In addition, during the period of World War I, he wrote a regular column for the Chicago Tribune.
Scope Note
The Robert Herrick Papers contain correspondence; manuscripts of novels, plays, short stories, and literary criticism. The collection also includes essays and lectures on political, educational, and literary subjects. Herrick's correspondents include Robert Morss Lovett, Jane Addams, William Dean Howells, Harriet Monroe, William Rainey Harper, Norman Hapgood, and Bernard Berenson.
There are ten series in this collection, which include:
I. Correspondence
II. Autobiographical Documents
III. Literary Manuscripts
IV. Essays and Lectures
V. Teaching Notes
VI. World War I Papers, Articles, and Memorabilia
VII. Virgin Island Papers
VIII. Reviews of Novels
IX. Legal-Sized
X. Miscellaneous Correspondence, Interviews, and Ephemera
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937; Harper, William Rainey, 1856-1906; Herrick, Robert, 1868-1938; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Lovett, Robert Morss, 1870-1956; Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936; Nevius, Blake; Virgin Islands of the United States-Politics and government
INVENTORY
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Subseries 1: Robert Herrick with Robert Morss Lovett 1893-1938
    - 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1908-1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1920-1929 (1 from Philip Herrick) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Envelopes for letters sent to Robert Morss Lovett, circa 1893-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Subseries 2: Selected Correspondence
    - Clyde Fitch to Robert Herrick 1901-1908 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    - Alice Freeman Palmer and George Herbert Palmer to Robert Herrick 1893-1916 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, A-W, Addams, Jane Fuller, Henry Blake Garland, Hamlin (4) Grant, Robert (5) Howells, William Dean (9) James, Henry (4) James, William Monroe, Harriet Moody, William Vaughn (13) Payne, Will (26) Wharton, Edith (2) (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: General Correspondence 1893-1935
    - 1893-1895, Bird, F. M. Etheridge, Mary Lee Fullerton, W. Morton (6) Goodspeed, T. W. (2) Hapgood, Norman (12) Harper, William Rainey (2) Herrick, Lucius C. & Herrick genealogy notes Herrick, Mr. & Mrs. Robert Welch "at home" card & wedding announcement Hight, C. A. Low, Will H. Shiland [?], Fay Tarbell, Frank Envelope with note regarding Herrick's comment on Norton's translation of Dante Clipping from Harvard Alumni Bulletin with photograph of Mermaid Club; included are G. Santayana, G. R. Carpenter, Norman Hapgood, Jefferson Fletcher, Robert Herrick (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1896, Berenson, Bernhard (9) Costelloe, Mary Dyer, Louis Fullerton, W. M. Hale, W. G. Hapgood, Norman (2) Hapgood, Hutchins Herrick, Robert to William Rainey Harper Laughlin, J. Laurence (3) Loeser, Charles (4) Muir, John Pajet [?], V. Perry, Thomas Sergeant (7) Schofield, William Henry (3) Unidentified & incomplete (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1897-1899, Bradley, C. B. Clark, Louise Cottman, George S. Cowan, James M. Fletcher, Jefferson B. Harper, William Rainey Hapgood, Hutchins Hapgood, Norman (3) Hight, C. A. (2) Laughlin, J. Laurence Lewis, E. H. Low, Will H. (3) Marquis, A. N. & Co. McLean, Mary D. Nicoll, W. Robertson Perry, Thomas Sergeant Shepardson, Francis W. Tarbell, Frank White, James T. Wigmore, John H. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1900-1902, Boyesen, P. K. Goodspeed, T. W. Hall, Charles M. Hapgood, Norman (3) Harper, William Rainey To R. M. Lovett Herrick, Robert to Carpenter Linn, James W. Lovett, Ida Low, Will H. (3) Manly, John M. Martin, Florence Monroe, Susie (née Calhoun q.v.) Moulton, Louise Chandler Salter, William M. Smith, Mary R. Sprague, Lucy Tarbell, Frank B. Wheeler, Benjamin Ide (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1903-1904, Abbot, Edwin H. Abbot, Edwin H., Jr. Abbot, N. I. Alger, George W. Baker, George P. Bigd, Mary Blanchard, Ferdinand Breckenridge, Isabella Goodrich Carpenter, Frederick I. Carpentier, G. R. SEE Box 2, Folder 19 Century Association Cook, Grace L. Cowdin [?], Gertrude Ditwell [?], Sallie J. Droppers, Garrett Eliot, Margaret D. Etheridge, Mary Lee Fairbanks, Janet Ayer Gilman, Bradly Gilman, Edith to Isabel Hackett, Frank S. Hapgood, Neith Harper, William Rainey Jones, Jenkin Lloyd Jones, Thomas D. (2) Lewis, E. H. Low, Berthe Low, Will H. (3) Lyman, F. G. Mabie, Hamilton W. Martin, Florence (2) Matthews, Brander Munsterberg, A. Nixon, E. Peabody, Jeannette B. Salter, William M. Searby, Ellen W. Southgate, Charles M. (2) Sprague, O. S. A. Wells, Chauncey W. (2) Wheeler, Benjamin Ide University of California Bulletin, summer session, 1902 Lease on 5727 Lexington Ave. house, May 1903-December 1903 List of names of people to whom copies of Common Lot were sent (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1905-1906, Arkmonoff, E. (2) Aldis, Arthur T. Bowers, Roy Edwin Calhoun, Susie Carpenter, Frederic I. Dyer, Louis Flint, Edith (2) Goodspeed, T. W. Harper, William Rainey Herrick, Robert to Martin A. Ryerson (2) Hutchinson, Frances K. Judson, Harry Pratt Low, Berthe Mallory, Leila Fish Marsh, Helen F. Martin, Florence (2) Nielson, Harold Palmer, Frederic Robertson, David A. Robertson, George E. Sturmer, Herbert H. Tarbell, Frank Young, A. V. E. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1907-1908, Aldis, Mary Allen, Charles W. Angliu, Margaret to Mr. Hapgood Barker, Mabel H. Carpenter, G. R. (2) Carpenter, Mary Clark, Louise (2) Coke, Billet Bradford Cragin, W. H. Dixon, Josephine Elliston, Grace to William Moody Feurer, Madge Barton Fletcher, Horace Fuller, Lucia F. Gehring, Dr. J. G. (6) Goodspeed, T. W. Gregory, Sarah E. Hapgood, Neith Herrick, Myron T. Hollander, Lee M. Judson, Harry Pratt Judson, Rebecca A. Klebs, Arnold Macgowan, P. S. Malone, Walter Martin, Florence (2) McCundy, Allen W. Nielsen, Harold Richberg, D. E. H., envelope only Sprague, Lucy Stead, William T. (2) Van Norman-Crane, B. Washburne, Marion Foster Wilson, Louise Gibbons One envelope with list of names (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1909-1914, Angell, James R. (2) Björkmann, Edwin Browne, T. B., Ltd., per J. Forteus Burton, Richard Councilman, W. T. Lallie, Norbert (3) Phillips, John S. Potter, N. B. Rublee, George Sching, Ar. Sedgwick, H. D. (2) Wallace, Elizabeth Youg [?], James Carleton (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1915, Balagnini, G., with 2 enclosures Bergson, H. (2) Bryan, W. J. Ellis, Elizabeth W. Garnier, N. (3) Hazen, George H. Herrick, Myron T. (7) Page, L. W. (2) Stanton, L. D. Wheeler, J. R. (2) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1916, Bangs, Edith [B? ], Betsey Breckenridge, Isabella Goodrich Cadwalander, John Castle, W. R., Jr. Cunliffe, J. W. Droppers, Garrett Duvernoy, Georges (3) Evans, Colette Hanotaux, Gabriel Herrick, Myron T. (3) Hibben, Paxton Jusserand, J. J. Lane, A. Miller, A. C. Peabody, Mary C. Ryerson, Martin A. Shaler, Sophia P. Proof of advertisement, The World Decision (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1917-1919, Andrew, A. Platt Arkmonoff, E. (2) Brooks, V. W. (2) Carter, June Benedict Duvernoy, Georges (2, part missing) Harvey, E. L. (2) Leger, A. Séguin, E. Tardieu, Andrè Unidentified (2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1921-1930, Aldis, Mary, Receipt Burton, Ernest D. Cashen, John F., Jr. (4) Christian, George B., Jr. (2) Cutting, Bronson Dickerson, J. Spencer (3) Duvernoy, Georges Eyer, Ernest Q. Garnier, Renée Hanson, J. C. M. Harding, Warren G. Manly, John M. Rosaire, Forrest Sartiaux, Albert Stibgen, Geary V. Swain, J. D. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1931-1935, Anderson, Winslow S. Angell, James (2) Arvin, Newton Baldwin, Roger N. Clemens, Cyril Cowley, Malcolm (3) Daniel, Cyril E. Davis, Morris E. Fagin, N. B. Herrick, Robert to Ernest Gruening (4) Herrick, Robert to Governor Cramer Herrick, Robert to Arthur Garfield Hays Herrick, Robert to E. Kuntz Keogh, Andrew Laing, G. J. Ludecke, [?] Ruhl, Arthur Sargent, T. Manlius Visa application (U.S.S.R.), with photograph of Herrick D. Publisher, Agents 1893-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1897 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1898 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1899 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1900 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1903 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1904 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1905 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1906-1912 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1913-1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1925-1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1933-1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series II: Autobiographical Documents
  - Clippings and Memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Myself" [begun 1913, revised 1915?] typescript, 119 pp. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "The Love Book," Sept. 29, 1916, holograph, 48 leaves (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Mr. Maggot's Fortune," Sept. 1931, typescript, 29 pp., text and notes (He intended to include this in "This Mad World," below.) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "One's Place in the World" [between 1931 and 1933?] typescript, 45 pp. (He intended to include this in "This Mad World.") (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Chapters" [during the Hoover administration?] typescript, 19 pp. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "This My Life," Jan. 1, 1931, with additions dated March 1934, typescript, 105 pp., numbering irregular (See also "One's Place in the World," "Mr. Maggot's Fortune," and "This Mad World." (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "This Mad World," June 6, 1933, typescript, 67 pp. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Autobiographic MSS 1907-1933, "Early Morning Wisdom," Oct. 3, 1907, holograph, 1 p. Genealogical Notes [n.d.] typescript, 2 half sheets "The Diary of an Intravert," Jan. 24, 1924, typescript, 9 leaves Untitled fragment: begins "E. belongs markedly... typescript, 2 short leaves (See also "The Diary of an Intravert" and "Magic" in Wanderings.) "Leaves from the Diary of a Wanderer," 1926, 1927, typescript, 2 leaves "The Stream of Life" [1925 or 1926?] typescript, 2 chapters: "The Stream of Life," 5 pp.; "The Idols of My Youth," 5 pp. "My Last Book," Jan. 1928, typescript, 9 pp. "Personal Data," June 22, 1931, typescript, 6 pp. "In Search for One's Soul," Nov. 1931, typescript, 1 p. No title, brown paper, holograph, 1 p. list of places Herrick lived in or visited from 1921 to 1935 Untitled fragment: begins "Apropos Granville Hicks..." [1933?] typescript, 2 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series III: Literary Manuscripts
  - Subseries 1: Published Novels
    - Gospel of Freedom, 1898, Part 1, holograph, early version (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Gospel of Freedom, Part 2, holograph, early version (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "With the Multitude" (early title for The Web of Life, 1900), chapters 1-3, holograph, early version (See also Box 15, Folder 2; and Box 24, Folders 3-6.) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "With the Multitude," chapters 4-7 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Real World, 1901, holograph, minor differences between this and published version changes probably made while proof-reading (Box 4, Folder 6-11)
    - Jock O Dreams (early title for The Real World), holograph, fragments (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Jock O Dreams, holograph, fragments (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - The Common Lot, 1904, holograph, 1st rough draft, notebooks 1-5 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Common Lot, notebooks 6-8 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Common Lot, notebooks 9-11 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Common Lot, notebooks 12-13 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, 1905, holograph, MS A, incomplete 1st draft (See legal-sized boxes at the end of the collection for serial version.) (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, holograph, MS B, sheets from 2nd draft (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, holograph, MSS C1, C2, C3, third draft? (This version is written in the third person.) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, holograph, MSS D1, D2, fourth draft? (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, holograph, MS E, fifth draft (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, MS E, fifth draft (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, MS E, fifth draft (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, holograph, MS F, sixth draft (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Memoirs of an American Citizen, MS F, sixth draft (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Together, 1908, holograph, incomplete, not final version, notebooks 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Together, notebooks 3-4 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Together, notebooks 5-6 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Together, notebooks 7-8 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Together, holograph, only part III, early version (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Together, holograph, sheets from 1st rough draft and play version (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - His Great Adventure, 1913, holograph, early version, notebook (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - His Great Adventure, holograph, early version, 2 notebooks (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Clark's Field, 1914, typescript, not final version (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Homely Lilla, 1923, typescript, minor differences between this and published version (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - "Chapter A" [n.d.] typescript, fragment and 1 p. notes (Cf. Waste, 1924) (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - A University Novel, notes and fragments (Cf. Chimes, 1926.), "A Modern Academe," holograph, 2 leaves "The Founder," holograph, 12 leaves "A Modern Academe," holograph, 10 leaves No title: begins "The Dean," holograph, notes 1 p. "Pleasant Walks of Academe," holograph and typescript, notes 1 leaf "Pleasant Walks of Academe," typescript, 1 leaf "The Story of Jessica Stowe," typescript, 2 leaves (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The End of Desire, 1932, typescript, early version, incomplete and notes, 1 p., titled "Themes and Notes for Jessica at Fifty" (See also Story of Jessica Stowe," above and "Tides," Box 10, Folder 2) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "The New Book" (early title for Sometime, 1933), typescript, notes, fragments (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Unpublished Novels
    - "The Real Story of a Woman's Life" [Harvard period] holograph, 1st half (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - "The Real Story of a Woman's Life," 2nd part, end missing (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "The Family" [begins thinking of this in 1911] holograph, notebooks 1-2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "The Family," holograph, notebooks 3-4 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "The Family," typescript, volume I, version A (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "The Family," May 30, 1914, typescript, volume I, version B (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "The Family," typescript, fragment (Cf. "The Family," volume I, version A.) (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "The Family," typescript, fragment (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - "A Song in the Heart," March 31, 1931, holograph, 2 notebooks (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Heart of Man" [1919] holograph notes, typescript text and fragments (Cf. Waste. See also Box XVI, Folder 3.) (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "The Almoners" [n.d.] typescript, 1st draft of "Aladdin's Almoners"? (Cf. Chimes.) (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "Aladdin's Almoners" [1920's?] typescript, pseudonym Benjamin Lunt on title page, 2nd draft? (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "Aladdin's Almoners," typescript, 3rd draft? (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Papers relating to "Tides" [1920's], "Foreward to Jessica," typescript, 3 leaves Notes for "Jessica at Fifty" and "Tides," typescript, fragment, 4 leaves "Tides," typescript, notes, 7 pp., whole and short sheets (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Tides," typescript text, with handwritten notes by E. C. Parsons; varying versions (Cf. The End of Desire, 1932.) (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
    - Papers relating to "Tides" [1920's], "Is Monogamy Feasible?" printed pamphlet by E. C. Parsons (Cf. The End of Desire.) "Memoranda for Travel in the World and in Life," Feb. 16, 1925, typescript, 1 leaf "Field Trip, Number Three," typescript, 1 leaf Envelope for "Tides" and "Jessica," note by R. M. Lovett (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "The Lake," Aug. 1931, typescript, 1 p. notes, text, -large envelope titled "Private Papers, MS Notes for Novels" (See also "This Mad World," below.) (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - "This Mad World" [1933?] typescript, 2 pp. notes, text (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "The Stilson Trail," 1934, typescript, notes, text, fragments (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Microcosm," typescript (part of "The Stilson Trail") (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3: Short Fiction
    - "The Great Unknown" [1892?] holograph, incomplete, 12 pp. Untitled fragment [early] holograph, 2 leaves (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "The Spirit of the Cloister" [1893?] holograph, fragment (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "A Question in Art," 1893, holograph, published in Literary Love Letters, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "Literary Love Letters," 1893, holograph, published in Literary Love Letters (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - "A Monologue of Lovers" [1894 or later?] holograph (Cf. One Woman's Life.) (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Short fiction, "Remnof's Story" [1894?] typescript and holograph, rejected by Youth's Companion, 1894 (See Box 2, Folder 12.) "Emigration of the Calkins," 1895, printed version (Cf. "Squalor," The Harvard Monthly, 10, April, 1890, 59-64.) (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - "A Prothalamium," 1895, holograph, published in Literary Love Letters (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - "Mare Morto," 1897, holograph, published in Literary Love Letters (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - "A Temporary Infidelity," 1897, holograph, published in Love's Dilemmas, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - "On the Ice," 1899, typescript (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - "The Call of the Wind," 1899-1900, holograph and typescript, 2 versions (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified fragment [1899-1900?] holograph (university background) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Short Fiction, 1900-1902, "The Professor's Chance," 1900, typescript and holograph, published in Atlantic Monthly, 87 (May, 1901), 723-732 "The Opinion of the World" [1902] galley proof, story withdrawn 1905 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Their Child, 1903, holograph, early version (See also legal-sized boxes at the end of the collection.) (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "The Dominion of Sin: [1904?] holograph, rejected by Lippincott's (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Short Stories, 1906, holograph, black notebook, "The General Manager," published Scribner's, 43 (March 1908), 270-282 "Papa's Stratagem," published Collier's, 40 (Oct. 19, 1907), 21-23 "Tea Table Literature" "A Manufactured Article" "The Breath of the Moment" Printed copies of: "The General Manager" "Papa's Stratagem" "Temple of Juno" "The Home," typescript (Cf. Master of the Inn.) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "The Avalanche," 1907, holograph, published Scribner's, 41 (June 1907), 705-714 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - The Master of the Inn, July 1907, holograph, sheets from the first draft, "Who Was the Master of the Inn?" [n.d.] typescript (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - "Their Honeymoon" [n.d.] typescript, 2 versions (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "The Gas House" [1909?] typescript (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - "Mdle Beata," typescript (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "Where Love Lies" [n.d.] typescript, earliest version? (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - "Where Love Lies," typescript, another version (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - "Where Love Lies," typescript, final version (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - "Man Is" [1910?] typescript, 2 versions (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - "The House" [1910?] typescript (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - "The White Faced Bull" [n.d.] typescript, 2 versions (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "The Flaw in the Metal" [n.d.] typescript, 2 versions (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - "The Rainbow Chasers," 1914, typescript and holograph, published Canadian Magazine, 44 (December 1914), 175-186 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Short Fiction, "Adele at War" [World War I period] typescript, early version "Adele Goes to War," typescript, later version "Adele at Peace," typescript "Art," typescript (about Adele) (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Incomplete fiction [about 1916?] typescripts, "The Lady in Green," notes, 1 p. "Their Love," 1 p. notes and text No title: begins " A love story with the background of the tropics," 1 p. notes and text "Love's Prelude" and "A Prelude," earlier version "The Call" "The Love Book" (Box 11, Folder 20)